<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true representation to the King and people of England how matters were carried on all along in Ireland by the late King James in favor of the Irish papists there from his accession to the crown, to the tenth of April, 1689 / by an impartial eye-witness.</title>
            <author>Impartial eye-witness.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3098</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24644</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08259089</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08259089</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1242:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true representation to the King and people of England how matters were carried on all along in Ireland by the late King James in favor of the Irish papists there from his accession to the crown, to the tenth of April, 1689 / by an impartial eye-witness.</title>
                  <author>Impartial eye-witness.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41254:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41254:1"/>
            <p>A True Repreſentation TO THE KING and PEOPLE of ENGLAND; How Matters were carried on all along in IRELAND BY THE <hi>Late King James,</hi> In Favour of the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> there: From His Acceſſion to the CROWN, To the Tenth of <hi>April,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By an Impartial Eye-Witneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENS'D, <hi>Aug.</hi> 16. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41254:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41254:2"/>
            <head>A True Repreſentation to the King and People of <hi>England,</hi> how Matters were carried on all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Late King <hi>James,</hi> in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO ſatisfie thoſe that make it their buſineſs to reflect on the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who left <hi>Ireland</hi> in the late Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities; the following <hi>Reaſons</hi> are briefly offered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is clearly evident, That <hi>Ireland</hi> is a Kingdom depending on <hi>England,</hi> and that the Acts paſſed in it are to be altered, amended, and confirmed by the King and Council of <hi>England,</hi> as by <hi>Poyning</hi>'s Act in <hi>Ireland,</hi> may more fully appear. That <hi>England</hi> receiv'd K. <hi>J.</hi> as their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, is likewiſe granted; and that <hi>Ireland</hi> intirely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, is evident: And here I will not enter into a tedious diſcourſe of all the meaſures taken ſince 1660, to ſubvert the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and the Laws Eſtabliſhed, (<hi>which will be ſhortly at large ſet forth,</hi> by another Hand, <hi>to the full ſatisfaction of every Impartial and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprejudiced per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>) but briefly and truly give an account of the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince his Acceſſion to the Crown. It is plain, that his whole endeavours were bent to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery, and eſtabliſh it in theſe Kingdoms, and that he could not more readily effect it, and try the Genius of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects of <hi>Ireland</hi> (who were taught to yield him Paſſive Obedience, by the eaſie compliance of ſome of their Party then in power, to his fierce Incroachments) than by a new modelling of the Army there; which in a very little time was ſo purged, that ſcarce a true <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or honeſt Gentleman was left in it: And tho' it began by degrees whilſt his Excellency the Lord <hi>Clarendon</hi> had the Sword, yet it was fully executed (to the almoſt ruine of many a worthy Gentleman, whoſe fortune depended on it) a little
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41254:3"/>after the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had the honour of being his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that Kingdom. This being the firſt ſtep, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were made Officers, and Troops and Companies filled every where with them, and were trained and exerciſed by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary diligence of ſome good old Officers, kept in I ſuppoſe of purpoſe for it, who ſoon became, not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of their <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Commanders, but were preferred to their places. So that the Sword (and conſequently the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary command of that Kingdom) was wholly in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The next thing to be looked into was the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and he who was known to be a true <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> was laid aſide, and new Judges of the right ſtamp were firſt Coyned, who had command in their reſpective Circuits to inform the Government of all <hi>Proteſtant Juſtices</hi> (or <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>'s favorers as they called them) who were likewiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently eaſed of their Commiſſions, and all other Impoloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Then the Officers of the Revenue were alſo purged; and ſeveral of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> who had got in among them (in infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Stations) yet in regard they were not ſo well qualified as the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by a knowledge in thoſe affairs, ſome were removed, and the moſt uſeful of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> reſtored for a while; yet as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> grew skilful, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſtill were outed again: Matters being thus acted and the <hi>Proteſtant No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> and many of the Gentry knowing of no better Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent than to come into <hi>England</hi> (ſince they could not ſtruggle againſt the King's will, which was a Law in <hi>Ireland</hi>) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they removed hither to make a Remonſtrance of the Grievances of that Kingdom to the late King: and tho' they flock'd over out of all parts, yet they prevailed ſo little to gain any redreſs, that they ſaw plainly they could not return into <hi>Ireland</hi> without apparent hazard of their Lives.</p>
            <p>And now was it judged by the Ld. Deputy the fitteſt time for him to put his long contrived deſigns <hi>of Subverting the Proteſtant Religion, and introducing</hi> Popery, <hi>into full Execution;</hi> upon which in <hi>November</hi> laſt, there was a motion made in Council for diſarming all the reſt of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41254:3"/>Kingdom, which being known, and moſt concluding that as ſoon as their Arms were taken (there being then a hot Diſcourſe of a general Maſſacre intended) 'twas only to leave them more naked and expoſed, ſo as that might have its full effect more eaſily, and with leſs oppoſition upon them, which alarm'd the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſo, that many thouſands came flocking over to avoid that fatal ſtroke. Now were the few <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who lived diſperſt left to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. In the mean time the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> (who ſtill had the Sword undemanded and undiſpoſed of to any other) iſſues new Commiſſions, not only to the <hi>Ro. Ca.</hi> who had ſome Eſtates; but to all, who were willing to ſtand up for the Cauſe, that were men of broken Fortunes and worſe Fame, but could influence the Rabble and raiſe Companies, only with this Salvo, that they ſhould maintain them for 3 months on their own coſt and charge, and then they ſhould have their Commiſſions given them: by which it was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, that in regard there was but little Money in the Treaſury, they ſhould be fitted for ſervice againſt the time K. <hi>J.</hi> ſhould come, or ſend them Money; or, that if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty found an Army ready to Land out of <hi>England,</hi> what Money was there would be little enough to bear his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and furniſh him with Neceſſaries on his flight. But theſe Commiſſions (or rather Incouragements) being very many, for every one who could get about 60 <hi>Kearnes,</hi> or Country Fellows to joyn with them, and own him as their Captain, immediately ſtrutted and looked very big, and was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, by the name of Captain; ſo that it was nothing ſtrange to have 20 or 30 Companies in a County, and theſe the noted Idlers and Cow-ſtealers. So that preſently the Captains (many of which had not 3 Cows of their own) had ſeveral ſcores of Cattle driven into Nooks and By-Paths; and all that were branded, were ſure to go to Pot, in regard the <hi>Horne</hi> (as they called it) ſpoke <hi>Engliſh;</hi> the reſt were ſent into other remote <hi>Counties</hi> to the Officers there, and thoſe again ſent their ſtolen Cattle in exchange
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41254:4"/>for the other (which was done to elude a Proclamation from the Lord Deputy on the many and daily Complaints and Petitions he receiv'd on account of the ſtolen Cattle) requiring all Officers and Soldiers as well as others to be aiding and aſſiſting to recover the ſtolen Cattle, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Offenders; which paſs'd for currant. For it was well if a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> could go ſafe to the Captain of the next Garriſon, who ſometimes would be ſo civil (eſpecially if a Sum of money were given his men to aſſiſt in the ſearch) as to ſend 8 or 10 miles, but be ſure the Cattle muſt be far enough from the place ſearched; and ſometime when 30 or 40 good fat Bullocks came to be made a Prey, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a 3d or 4th part muſt be laid aſide for the Pot; the reſt for a Bribe of 5 or 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> would be got by ſome of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who would ſwear luſtily they were forced to promiſe ſo much to their Spy: Yet no ſooner (on the delivery of the greater part of the Cattle, and the money receiv'd) but be ſure in a night or two the Cattle were again ſtolen. Thus the merry Drovers (as they called themſelves) valued not to joyn about 60, or 80, or 100 in one Party, and force away what Cattle they had a mind to: ſo that ſometimes 100 Sheep would ſcarce feed the Drivers with their Families and Friends; and a purchace of about 100, was only fit to be divided among them and their Crew into Lots and Parts, (but they called them <hi>Steages.</hi>) And now theſe new rais'd Forces were moſt of them half armed out of the Stores, the reſt were pretty well fitted for Pikes made in the Country, and the Prieſts and Fryars commanded (on obedience to the Holy See) that no perſon whatſoever ſhould appear at Maſs without his long <hi>Skeane</hi> and <hi>Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pike,</hi> which accordingly was performed, and one perſon who had not one foot of Land but what he Farmed from an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, had 12 dozen of each made for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Tenants, an account whereof was ſent the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but no notice taken.</p>
            <p>And now was it judged fit that <hi>thoſe new rais'd forces</hi> ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41254:4"/>betake themſelves to Garriſons, which was ſuddainly done —And not only were the Kings Garriſons, Forts, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, well ſtored with them, but many Gentlemens houſes that were ſtrengthy, (or whoſe ownes were judged diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to them) were likewiſe filled with their Numbers, and the Proprietors, or Poſſeſſors turned out, and the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſeized, (and it was an extraordinary favour to get off any Goods that were of any value) on pretence that it was for the Kings uſe, and that he would make ſatisfaction as he thought fit, and that it was done by his Command.</p>
            <p>Now was it plain, that this Army was not deſigned to fight with Butterflies, and that the Lives of all the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> that ſtayed, were in apparent danger: On which an humble requeſt was made to one or two perſons of greateſt Quality and Station, to ſtand up for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> — But either through too much Loyalty, or judging the ſcattered and diſperſed <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> too weak to withſtand their ſhock, (much leſs to diſarm the Party deſigned) was therefore declined and judged unfit to attempt as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ſeizing the Sword, Lord Deputy, and <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matters being thus tranſacted, it was judged by the <hi>Proteſtant Gentry</hi> of the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that in regard <hi>Sligoe,</hi> (which is a Sea-port Town, and the chief in the County) one of the beſt Poſts and ſtrongeſt, being alſo well ſituated to paſs from the <hi>North</hi> to <hi>Connaght;</hi> (the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Company a little before being drawn out of it to a General Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz) and many of their new raiſed Forces poſſeſſing them ſelves daily of the moſt conſiderable ſtrengths in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Belahy, Moygara,</hi> which belongs to the L. <hi>Kingſton</hi> and his Tenants, <hi>Ouſted,</hi> and <hi>Ballymoate;</hi> therefore, leſt they ſhould likewiſe poſſeſs themſelves of <hi>Sligo</hi> as they intended, it was reſolved by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there to enter it, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs themſelves of it for their defence and ſafety: and ſo they did unanimouſly iſſue their Declaration on the <hi>4th</hi> day of <hi>Jan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar.</hi> laſt, that they aſſociated themſelves in the neceſſary defence of their Lives and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion as by Law
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41254:5"/>eſtabliſhed,</hi> which to their utmoſt powers they would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and would not prejudice even <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> whilſt they demeaned themſelves according to the Laws —The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> then choſe the Right Honorable <hi>Robert</hi> L. Baron of <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> and the Honor. <hi>Chidley Coote,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in chief, to whom they promiſed intire obedience. —And accordingly all were formed into Troops and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and all furniſhed themſelves with the Men under their reſpective Commands, with Horſes, Arms, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Proviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> imploying all the Smiths in fixing Arms, making Pikes, Stars, and other Inventions againſt Horſe, and to defend Forts, buying all the Scythes, and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them on Poles, building up the old and decayed Forts, making Draw bridges, ordering frontier Garriſons, keeping ſtrong Watch and Ward on all Quarters, at <hi>Grange</hi> near Mid-way to <hi>Baliſhannon,</hi> to hold their Correſpondence with <hi>Derry,</hi> at <hi>New-town, Dromahere,</hi> and <hi>Mannerhamelton,</hi> to have intelligence with <hi>Enniskilling,</hi> at Dr. <hi>Leſlies,</hi> at <hi>Coolooni,</hi> and <hi>Marcray,</hi> to prevent an infal from the <hi>Boyle,</hi> or <hi>Ballymoate;</hi> at <hi>Ardinglaſs, Lackan,</hi> and <hi>Cottleſtown,</hi> to awe the new rais'd Army in the County of <hi>Mayo,</hi> part of which had ſeized the Biſhop of <hi>Killalla</hi>'s Houſe: And when one Mr. <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> (a Servant of Sir <hi>Arthur Gore</hi>'s) ask'd one Captain <hi>Walter Bourke</hi> why he would ſeize the Biſhop's Houſe, and make it a Garriſon, the Gate was ſhut upon him, and he ſet upon and barbarouſly murthered. Likewiſe an Account of the Proteſtants, who were at <hi>Foxford,</hi> and many other places, who were drawing to <hi>Sligo</hi> on the Orders that iſſued for diſarming all Proteſtants of the Kingdom; as alſo to take all their Service-Horſes, which was obeyed with that Secrecy, Diligence, and Care, that not ſo much as a Plow-Horſe was left; ſo that many a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, for want of a Horſe to carry their Luggage, was forced to ſtay and ſubmit to their mercileſs Cruelty; but this Garriſon relieved and conveyed many a diſtreſſed and robbed Proteſtant to <hi>Sligo,</hi> who ſoon was recruited
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41254:5"/>and put into Troop or Company at the Officers coſt. During this time there was a ſecret Intreague with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Ellis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Temple:</hi> As alſo a ſham Letter from the Lord <hi>Tyrconel</hi> into <hi>England</hi> about delivering the Sword; and had there one been ſent to demand the Sword with about a Thouſand Soldiers, 'tis not doubted but it would be delivered, though at the ſame time the Lord <hi>Montjoy</hi> (leaſt he ſhould ſtand up for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) is Complemented with an Embaſſy into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Iriſh</hi> getting all this time to ſtrengthen themſelves, and the Arms and Horſes taken from the Proteſtants, they began to encreaſe to an Army of 90000. ſtrong: And all this while there was neither Commiſſion, Arms, Ammunition, or Money ſent to the Proteſtants at <hi>Sligo,</hi> notwithſtanding that as they were Informed, it was earneſtly ſollicited by a Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in <hi>England,</hi> who knew the goodneſs and ſtrength of that Poſt they were in, and that they daily expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Succours, ſo that the Proteſtants there began to be in very great want of Ammunition; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their endeavours, wanted many Arms, tho' all the fowling Pieces were cut into Carbines, and Smiths continually at work. And the Sword (to which the Supreme Acknowledgment is paid) was ſtill unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s hand, and ſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Command he would not lay it down; yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants at <hi>Sligo</hi> continued in their own and Proteſtant Religions defence, according to their Declaration of the Fourth of <hi>January,</hi> without any violation of it, and kept conſtant Watch and Ward with the uſual Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe againſt occaſion offered, only on account of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Proteſtants who were ſtopt at <hi>Boile,</hi> and their Goods ſeiz'd by Colonel <hi>Mac Donel,</hi> who poſſeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of my Lord <hi>Kingſton</hi>'s Houſe there, and likewiſe on all the Corn and Hay of his Tenants near it. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41254:6"/>ſaid Lord <hi>Kingſton</hi> writ to the Colonel, deſiring him to let the Proteſtants with their Goods come down, for he did not hinder any Papiſt to remove to him; which not being done, my Lord reſolved to deliver thoſe from their Reſtraints, and accordingly with a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Party of Horſe and Foot marched to <hi>Boile;</hi> but the Colonel hearing of my Lord's coming, drew in all his Men and Horſes into my Lord's Houſe and Court, and Capitulated, and let his Priſoners go; and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on Honour not to hinder any from joyning at <hi>Sligo;</hi> but no ſooner was my Lord and his Party gone, than the next day thoſe that heard of that Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and were deſirous to go thither, were all ſeized and kept cloſe Priſoners till the Aſſizes— About this time, which was the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> the unlucky De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration (pardon the Expreſſion) of the Second of <hi>February</hi> laſt, as being ſent before any Army was Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to back it, and was there receiv'd, which gave time to all Papiſts to lay down their Arms and repair to their reſpective Dwellings by the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>April</hi> laſt, &amp;c. which did ſo tye up all the Proteſtants from offering Violence, even to thoſe who ſome time before ſtole their Cattel, that the leaſt Violence was not offered them, in an abſolute and intire Obedience to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration; by which means they were encouraged to have pardon for their Villanies and Robberies, and told by the Prieſts, Fryars and Officers, that no Army would be ſent to ſuppreſs them: and therefore till the time li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, they ſhould let none know their Reſolutions, whether to lay down, or ſtand to their Arms.— Alſo the <hi>French</hi> Marqueſs <hi>Dupont</hi> landing in <hi>Kinſale,</hi> and going to <hi>Dublin</hi> about this time, was ſplendidly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd there by the Lord Deputy, who aſſured him it would not be long till an Army Landed in <hi>Ireland</hi> out of <hi>France,</hi> as alſo of King <hi>James</hi>'s going thither very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41254:6"/>ſpeedily, and a full account of what ſince hapned, which would not at all be credited by any Proteſtants, but that an Army would land out of <hi>England</hi> before any could come from <hi>France;</hi> but it was hoped the Marqueſs would not return back to <hi>France</hi> nor ſcape our Men at Sea — Intelligence being now receiv'd, and Account of the Army, and how Affairs ſtood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent back by Monſieur, it was judged expedient to march an Army with all ſpeed to the <hi>North,</hi> and ſuppreſs the Proteſtants there. Accordingly an Army came to <hi>Liſnegarvy</hi> which (after a little Diſpute, a great number of their Men falling on a ſmall Party of ours) made them quit their Ground.— The noiſe of this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory ſoon took wing, and gave them encouragement to Beſiege <hi>Colerain;</hi> and not being able to do any Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution on that ſide, drew off their Men to march them back to get over the Bridge above it, and ſo fall on that Town from the other ſide of the River, on which <hi>Colerain</hi> wanting truſty and good Officers in it to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the Rabble with the Inhabitants deſerted and left the Town, (excepting only thoſe that reſolved to ſubmit to the Enemy) by which means, and the great diſorder they were in to get to <hi>Derry,</hi> many a good Horſe and Arms, as well as the Riches of that Town, fell into the Enemies hands.— Notice of theſe Diſaſters being immediately ſent from <hi>Derry</hi> by Colonel <hi>Lundee</hi> to the Gentlemen, who kept Garriſons in their Houſes in the Counties of <hi>Monaghan, Cavan,</hi> &amp;c. who were earneſtly deſired to draw down immediately with their Men, and joyn <hi>Derry</hi> Men; and underſtanding the Condition <hi>Derry</hi> was in, marcht forthwith: And leſt the Enemy ſhould poſſeſs themſelves of their ſtrong Houſes, Goods, and Proviſions, ſet fire to all, and marcht away by the light of it; conſuming their own Goods and Houſes, to joyn with <hi>Derry</hi> Men, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41254:7"/>the Enemies marching thither to beſiege it. And though it might be judged, the Loyalty and Zeal of theſe Gentlemen need not be queſtion'd; yet hitherto there is but ſmall Proviſions made for them. And if it be asked what made them come over, 'tis eaſily anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Diviſions in <hi>Derry</hi> amongſt ſeveral there, (who hitherto have ſcaped being called to account for it, may be fear'd, were private Inſtruments) and who took on them the Command, and ordered Matters as they themſelves pleaſed, taking no advice but that of their own Pleaſures, gave ſuch plain occaſion of diſtruſt, that it was judged better by thoſe and other honeſt Gentlemen there, to come over and give an Account how matters were, than to ſtay in diſorder and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, when eſpecially they were not able to ſtem the Current that ſo violently run againſt them, and whoſe buſineſs it was to joyn and aſſiſt with the Governour, rather than to give him publick oppoſition, when pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Advice proved vain; ſo that as well to avoid mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinying with him, as to bring a Calumny on themſelves, to be ſo much as ſuſpected for betraying that Intereſt and Religion they were not able to defend or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the Rabble being in Confuſion, who ſometime would have one, another day another Officer; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time would joyn themſelves, and do as they pleaſed. The one part of Proteſtants deſerting the other, and theſe not able to withſtand the Enemy without mutual aſſiſtance; and if they could, not daring to truſt their Governour, who was there (as well as he had been at <hi>Colerain</hi>) when they were about ſeizing him, and ſhut the Gates on him that he ſhould not get away, till by his Oaths of Fidelity to them, (which he freely gave) and a little Policy, he got off; and being under vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Suſpicions of a private Correſpondence with King <hi>James,</hi> who about this time was in <hi>Dublin,</hi> had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41254:7"/>created ſuch great Jealouſies, Feuds and Heart burnings in the Soldiers, he refuſing to give the Command to him choſen by the People: which was of no ſmall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Enemy, and daily weakned the Town, by the Deſertion of thoſe who durſt neither truſt him, nor themſelves under his Command.</p>
            <p>During theſe diſorders, Letters came to <hi>Sligo</hi> by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes one after another from the Colonel, deſiring my Lord <hi>Kingſton</hi> to ſend a Party to join them at <hi>Derry.</hi> But anſwer being immediately return'd him, that there were not men enow at <hi>Sligo</hi> to keep that Poſt (ſo far from all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and) in the Face of the Enemy, and of the want there was of Arms and Ammunition (which were then at <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to be had for Money.) Every Officer for himſelf and Men, ſent for ſo many as they wanted, according to their Proportions, and made a Purſe, and thought it convenient to ſend Captain <hi>Coote</hi> forthwith to acquaint them with the ſtate of the Garriſon and know theirs; — and bring Arms and Ammunition, which were very much want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; — whilſt another Letter came poſting, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a ſpeedy joining them at <hi>Derry.</hi> But a Council being call'd, it was reſolved to ſtay till Captain <hi>Coote</hi> returned and brought the certainty how Matters were, and not to quit that advantageous Poſt lightly, which coſt ſo much Money and Work to ſtrengthen it, and had ſo many Men, Women and Children, that had from almoſt all parts of <hi>Connaght</hi> flockt to it, and could not get room, nor be provided for at <hi>Derry;</hi> and above all, was ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to awe all <hi>Connaght</hi> Forces, that in caſe of Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Succours could come by Sea, which were now daily expected by every blaſt of an Eaſterly Wind, which was heartily wiſh'd and greedily long'd for. But ſtreight a third Expreſs was ſuddenly haſtened, ſhewing the great Danger the <hi>North</hi> was in; and if that were loſt, (as it was feared, without <hi>Sligo</hi>-Forces joining them, it would)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41254:8"/>that <hi>Sligo</hi> could not hold out long after, and earneſtly deſired to deſert it; and that he had provided Quarters and Forrage ready for them there, and come immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their relief. On which Expreſs another Council was held, and knowing the great want there was of Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (not much above one Barrel of Powder being in the Garriſon at <hi>Sligo,</hi>) and the Danger that threatned them at <hi>Derry,</hi> it was reſolv'd to join them forthwith, and quit <hi>Sliego,</hi> and to put all to the ſhort Iſſue of one Field-Fight. Accordingly all now reſolved to march with Bag and Baggage. The next day was ſpent in providing Horſes and Neceſſaries, in getting Boats, breaking the big Guns, and ſending of the ſmall to <hi>Derry</hi> by Water; burning and deſtroying all the Corn, Hay, and Haggards about the Country; calling in all the Frontier Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; — and every one uſing his utmoſt endeavours (ſome by Water to the Iſland of <hi>Eniſhmorrey,</hi> that was judged capable of defence till the Goods and Men could get off by Water to <hi>Derry,</hi>) the reſt with what Horſes they could get: ſo that the day following all marched; and a Veſſel lying then at <hi>Sligo,</hi> as many as could get off, with ſome Goods, the Wind being fair, ſailed away. But after two daies March (in the ſaddeſt Weather that could blow,) coming to <hi>Belaſhannon,</hi> 20 miles from <hi>Sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> a fourth Letter comes to my Lord, to ſtay him there till Quarters were provided for him, and Forrage got for Horſes; which was no ſmall ſurprize, after drawing him from his Poſt, on Aſſurance of providing thoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and of the diſtreſs that threatned <hi>Derry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Boat alſo with Paſſengers and Goods from <hi>Sligo</hi> was caſt away near <hi>Donigale,</hi> and another ſent with the Field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces, by reaſon of the Storm put into an <hi>Iſland,</hi> and the next day ſeiz'd and taken back, as were all the Goods, Proviſions, Men, and Women that went into the Iſland, which was no ſmall Booty. — But now was my Lord
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41254:8"/>
               <hi>Kingſton</hi> forced, for want of Forrage, to diſperſe his Men, ſome to <hi>Beleeke,</hi> ſome to <hi>Donigale,</hi> ſome to <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labegs</hi> (to keep <hi>Boylagh</hi> men in Awe, who were extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed, and began to rob publickly on <hi>Barneſmore,</hi>) ſome at <hi>Belaſhannon,</hi> and ſome about the County; and ſo continued for ſeventeen days in a very ill condition for want of Forrage, many of the Horſes being turned to Graſs for want of it, and the Weather continuing extreamly bad; which ſo abuſed them, that many were made unſerviceable. — At length a Letter comes from the Colonel to my Lord to <hi>Belaſhannon</hi> about ten at night, to ſecure the Paſs at <hi>Ballymofey</hi> (30 Miles thence) by ten next day, which was altogether impoſſible to be done; — neither could it be (under half that time) that the men could have notice of it ſent them, as they lay ſcattered in their ſeveral Quarters, which formerly I mentioned; and many were likewiſe to provide Horſes, their own being dead, or ſo weak and out of Condition for want of Forrage, that they were of little uſe for Service: However two Companies that were at and near <hi>Donnigale,</hi> march'd in the Morning betime to join the <hi>Northern</hi> Men, and to ſecure that Paſs, which was 20. Miles from them, and many hundreds of Men, Women and Children march'd with them, with Bag and Baggage in hopes to get to <hi>Derry</hi> before the Enemy intercepted them; but this day being diſmally wet, and extream windy, and marching over that horrible Mountain of <hi>Barneſmore,</hi> which is 15 miles long, tho' they marched at an extraordinary rate, yet it was ſeven at night before they could reach it; and my Lord (expecting to meet Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> there) rid with a dozen Horſe, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe him, and to know why he was drawn from his Poſt on pretence of ſo great danger? why he kept there in that bad condition ſo long after he had receiv'd his Letter, that Quarters and Forrage was provided for him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41254:9"/>and his Party? why he had not notice ſooner ſent him of the Enemies approaching ſo near? and how was it poſſible for him to march his Men, who lay ſcattered at ſuch a diſtance, under at leaſt three daies notice? but coming thither, there was ſoon an account given by thoſe, who that day were broke and fled from <hi>Cladyford</hi> Fight, that the Colonel, with the Horſe whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to go with him to ſecure a Paſs on the River above <hi>Cladyford,</hi> was gone to <hi>Derry;</hi> and it was not much queſtioned but the Enemy, who ſoon fell into <hi>Rapho,</hi> killing Men in the very Streets there, would be as ſoon at the Gate, and enter, as the Colonel.— And it is not much to be doubted, that had the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army Liberty of getting over that <hi>Ford,</hi> which they could not poſſibly do, without great danger of their Lives, the Water being ſo very high with that days rain, and the Bridge being broken down, that if they could have marched over and purſued their Victory, they would have got in without great (if any) oppoſition; for Colonel <hi>Cunningham,</hi> with the Succours ſent by him for the relief and defence of the Town, had ſet ſail, and reurned: and it was not doubted but <hi>Derry</hi> as well as <hi>Colerain,</hi> would be left to them by the Colonel, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that neither Men nor Arms were landed:— And now this Party thus diſappointed at <hi>Ballemofey,</hi> and the Enemy in <hi>Rapho</hi> between them and <hi>Derry,</hi> after this days ſad March, were now forced to return that night, over that wild Mountain; and Horſes being weak and weary with the long March and bad weather, could not get back that night, but were left with Loads and all: So that by much difficulty, and by the great care the two Companies of Foot (who brought up the Rear) took to bring off the Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who were ſadly toiled and tired, many of them would have been left and loſt, as almoſt all their Goods
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41254:9"/>and Baggage were. — And next Morning got back to <hi>Donigale,</hi> with much difficulty and diſtreſs, by reaſon of the badneſs of the Weather, as well as that of the way, and the Darkneſs, Windineſs, and Rain, contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not a little to the Hazards and Loſſes they ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. — And now conſulting what was to be done in theſe Diſorders, or rather treacherous Practices, it was concluded that my Lord <hi>Kingſton</hi> (with the Officers of his appointment that were there with him) ſhould come off in three or four Veſſels that lay at <hi>Killabeggs,</hi> and haſten over and give an account how matters were, and get Commiſſions and return with all ſpeed to their Friends, Relations and Tenants, whom they mounted and armed and ſent ſtraight to joyn <hi>Eniskillin</hi> Men; which was no ſmall trouble to them, that after about four months coſt, ſufferings, and acquaintance, they muſt now part, having neither Arms, Ammunition, nor Supplies ſent them: but it was now plain, that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel (who knew very well that King <hi>James</hi> was near his Army) which gave clear occaſions of diſtruſt, and that the private under-hand intelligence he held would be to the ruin of the Proteſtants; and the day after the Lord <hi>Kingſton,</hi> the wind being fair, ſet ſail. But to relate the miſeries and hardſhips they endured at ſea, lying a Ship-board like packt Herrings in their Boots and wet Cloaths for ſix or ſeven days, and twice like to be caſt away on the <hi>Scotch</hi> Shoar; and thence getting to <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow</hi> in ſmall Boats, ſome again riding poſt to <hi>London</hi> with my Lord, others going to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and then by Sea, ſome afoot to <hi>Leverpool</hi> above 200 miles, others again venturing, thither by Sea, who ever ſince have been waiting, petitioning, and expecting to return with Commiſſions for themſelves as well as for ſome of their Friends, who have given the World ſatisfaction of their Courage and Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and whoſe Names ought to be honoured with a perpetual
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41254:10"/>Remembrance of their Actions. And if the Archbiſhop of <hi>Tuam</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>Killalla,</hi> who very well knows my Lord, with the Gentlemen that came over with him, and what they did and ſuffered whilſt they were at <hi>Sligo,</hi> be enquired of the truth of this matter, that certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are provided for, and who never ſhewed that Zeal would not be preferred, and theſe (not only neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, by which means they ſuffer many hardſhips, but) even diſcountenanced, by being called Deſerters of their Country; and whether this uſage be not a Trial of their Zeal, I leave to any one to judge: alſo on due en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, or after what is ſaid, if they for coming over, or the Perſon who drew them from their Poſt, who by their Majeſties Commiſſion, was Governour of <hi>Derry,</hi> and who hazarded their Lives and Fortunes to join with him, without Commiſſions to oppoſe the Enemy, to be ſo ſerved, or he be moſt to blame?— Or whether they who know the Mountains, Creeks and Paſſes, as well as the notorious bloody Rebels and Cow-ſtealers, who have moſt of their neareſt Relations, either ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding their Lives againſt them, or under their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, at leaſt in reſtraint, with cruel uſage and hardſhips enough, if they have yet eſcaped with their Lives: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo that theſe Gentlemen, who have left their Goods, and come over, ſome with a very little Money, Plate, or other Moveables of value, which is now all ſpent; and ſome who have a great Charge of eight or ten in Family, who in probability might have ſtarved many of them, had not that charitable Courſe been taken for their ſupport; that is, who cannot raiſe Money here for want of City-ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; neither their own (tho they have good Eſtates in <hi>Ireland</hi>) nor the Gentlemen thence to be taken bound for them; whether, I ſay, theſe be able to return for want of Horſes, Arms, or Neceſſaries to carry them over, having ſpent all, and to carry a Musket, and leave their Families in want, and wholly unſettled and wanting Bread, would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41254:10"/>not only be bad encouragement for them, but that Pay would neither maintain them, nor ſcarce any one of their Familie; and whether a due conſideration and regard be not to be had of thoſe ſo quallified for Employments, and Perſons of known Courage and Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, of whom there are many unprovided for of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Employment, which would be a great eaſe to <hi>England</hi> in the ſeveral Sums paid for the Relief of thoſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who are now here in no capacity nor ability for providing for themſelves, tho they are ſufficiently zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for their Majeſties Service.</p>
            <p>And whether a farther delay may not be prejudicial as Matters ſtand, conſidering that for want of a ſpeedy relieving of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and not ſending over but about 100. Officers, and one to Command in Chief with Arm, Ammunition, Commiſſions, and Money in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, February, March,</hi> or <hi>April</hi> laſt, that Kingdom had not been wholly in the Proteſtants hands, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the French Army ſince Landed, as well as that raiſed by <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and if it had not prevented the ruin, Deſtruction, Deſolation, and Cruelties, which the Proteſtants there have ſince ſuffered?</p>
            <p>And now 'tis hoped it may not be amiſs to inſpect and enquire who the Retarders are; and to do it ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that they at length be fruſtrated of carrying on any farther Deſigns, to the Apparent ruin of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and to bring them to Condign Puniſhments for the Blood and Miſeries many Thouſands have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Cruelties, who were the Inſtruments who occaſion'd it. And whether they did not endeavour by ſuch Practices to Eſtabliſh Popery, as well as Confuſion.</p>
            <p>May they therefore be found out and made Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for their Perfidy. May their Sacred Majeſties ever be happy and defend the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from Popery and Superſtition, and have the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41254:11"/>Hearts of all their Subjects intirely united to them, whilſt all <hi>Ackitophels</hi> juſtly ſuffer. May <hi>England</hi> with all their Majeſties Kingdoms and Dominions flouriſh under Peace and Safety, whilſt we Bleſs God for his great Deliverances he wrought for us, in Placing their Majeſties on the Royal Throne. May the Poor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> Bleſs the Almighty, who they hope hath raiſed a Deliverer for them, that they may return in Peace to enjoy their Poſſeſſions; that they may make the right and Sanctified uſe of their Afflictions, ſo that they and their Children may never forget the great Deliverances wrought for them: Whilſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> be turned out of that Land, and receive their juſt demerits, and that Religion and true Piety, may ever flouriſh and be eſtabliſh'd among us for all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And may Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> have this alſo added to his former Renowned Acts, to prove the Deliverer, firſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants, and then of the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Anſwer of a Proteſtant Gentleman in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to a late Letter from <hi>N. N.</hi> upon a Diſcourſe betwixt them concerning the preſent Poſture of that Countrey, and the Part fit for thoſe concerned there to Act in it.</p>
            <p>An Aplogy for the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a Brief Narrative of the late Revolutions in that Kingdom, and an Account of the Preſent State thereof.</p>
            <p>The Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> in the Preſervation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Humbly preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>G. P.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <head>There is in the Preſs, and will be ſhortly Publiſhed</head>
            <p>A Full and Impartial Account of all the Secret Conſults, Negotiations, Stratagems, and Intrigues of the <hi>Romiſh Party</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Ireland,</hi> from 1660 to this preſent year 1689. for the Settlement of Popery in tha Kingdom.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
